Hi, I'm Dr. Halley
Zweibel, and today we're
going to be talking about
electrolyte disorders,
hyponatremia. By the end
of this presentation, you
should be able to distinguish
between the different
clinical features and
complications of hyponatremia.
You should be
able to illustrate
the pathophysiology
of hyponatremia.
You will be able to
judge the causes of
hyponatremia, explain the
treatment of hyponatremia,
and finally explain
the syndrome of
inappropriate antidiuretic
hormone secretion.
Let's start with a question.
What percentage of hospitalized
patients suffer
from hyponatremia?
The correct answer here is D,
20%, a pretty high percentage.
Next question.
A sodium level
below which of the
following is categorized
as hyponatremia?
The correct answer here is
less than 135 millimoles.
Therefore, by definition,
a sodium of less than 135
constitutes hyponatremia.
As we'll see, this
decreased sodium is
usually a result of
increased circulating
ADH or increased renal
sensitivity to ADH.
Let's talk about some
at-risk populations.
There's actually a
few to be aware of.
Patients in the ICU, post
-op patients, those with
psychiatric diagnoses,
as we'll see a little bit
later elderly patients
and specifically patients
who are residing in a
skilled nursing facility
which of the following
recreational drugs
has been shown to cause
acute hyponatremia
the correct answer here
is a mdma ecstasy or molly
it's a popular street
drug and it can result in
acute hyponatremia so that's
something to be aware of
What are some potential
complications of
acute hyponatremia?
The correct answer here
is all of the above.
Hyponatremia is really
an important topic.
It can cause cerebral
swelling, so water moves
down the osmotic gradient
from the extracellular
fluid to the intracellular
fluid, and neurologic
symptoms begin when we get
swelling of the brain within
that rigid skull. So
everything from seizures
to brain herniation can be
a really serious medical
problem and something
not to be taken lightly.
Now that we have a
little background on
hyponatremia, let's talk
about how we diagnose
a patient who we find
to have hyponatremia.
First, we always want to
look for an underlying cause.
Hyponatremia is
typically a manifestation
of one of several
issues going on.
This is especially true
in severe hyponatremia.
Therefore, it's often
getting multifactorial,
overwhelming the body's
natural systems to
maintain an equilibrium
of sodium concentration.
Few things to ask during your
history and to
examine your physical.
You should be asking
these patients when you
suspect hyponatremia
about a history of any
fluid loss. Why would
someone be losing fluids?
One reason could be if
they're suffering from
diarrhea. If they're
on diuretic therapy is
another one. You want to
get detailed medication
history, as we'll see
several medications
can cause hyponatremia
in addition diuretics.
We'll talk a little
bit more about SIADH
in detail later,
which is the syndrome
of inappropriate anti
-diuretic hormone.
This can result in
hyponatremia as well.
And just as in
hypernatremia, you want
to look for signs
of volume status.
So to recap, signs
of low volume
are decreased skin turgor,
decreased jugular venous
pressure. And when patients
have extra volume, we're
going to see peripheral
edema, ascites, and
findings of that nature.
After we go through
our physical exam, we
should be thinking about
laboratory studies.
A few key laboratory
studies can really
help us in determining
the reason why a
patient is suffering
from hyponatremia.
First is serum osmolarity.
osmolality rather serum
osmolality normally
ranges from about 275 to
290 milliosmoles per kg
and in most patients with
hyponatremia we're going
to see that this level
of serum osmolality is
reduced and we'll go through
a breakdown in further
detail after this but next
after looking at the serum
osmolality, we would look
at the urine osmolality.
The normal response
physiologically to hyponatremia
is markedly suppressed
ADH secretion. This
should result in excretion
of maximally dilute urine
with a urine osmolality
below 100 milliosmoles.
So that's normally what
should be happening if
everything's functioning
properly and the body encounters
a low serum osmolality
and a low sodium level.
Finally, we want to
look at the urine
sodium and chloride
concentration.
Patients with hyponatremia,
hypoosmolality,
and inappropriately
concentrated urine, the
urine sodium, and in
some settings, the urine
chloride concentrations
can be used distinguish
between different
hyponatremia diagnosis.
So with that
preface, let's talk
about how we classify
hyponatremia.
And when I talk about
classification, I'm talking
about a pathway we should
have in mind for breaking
down the different causes
and how to diagnose someone
with hyponatremia,
specifically identifying
the reason why.
So if we have a patient
with hyponatremia
like we said on the
previous slide we first
should be looking
at plasma osmolality
so plasma osmolality
can be broken down into
either high normal or low
and that's where we start
in terms of this algorithm
and as you can see
on the bottom here the
the names for these are
simple there's hypertonic
there's isotonic
hypotonic patients with
hyponatremia so isotonic
hyponatremia, hypertonic
hyponatremia, and so on.
And we'll go through
those individual causes
as we get further down
to this algorithm.
First, let's start
with patients with a
hyponatremia and a
high plasma osmolality.
This would be called
fictitious hyponatremia.
so here the plasma
osmolality would exceed 295
for it to be qualified as
high right now the rise
in serum sodium here is
induced by hyperglycemia
or mannitol and what's
happening is it's pulling
water out of cells so lowering
the sodium concentration
by dilution next if
we have a patient with
normal plasma osmolality,
we can think of several
different causes. And
this category is referred
to as pseudohyponatremia.
So as you might guess,
when the plasma osmolality
is higher normal, that
it's usually not what we're
talking about when we're
looking at cause of
hyponatremia. These are usually
the exceptions. So it's
important to know about them.
So pseudohyponatremia
will have a normal plasma
osmolality, so somewhere
between 280-295.
And what happens is
protein and lipids
occupy the plasma
volume, but they don't
contribute to the
plasma osmolality.
This will cause an apparent
decrease in the amount
of sodium per unit
volume when measured by
indirect laboratory
methods. So depending on the
lab that you're using,
they're either going to
measure serum sodium
directly or indirectly. And
when they measure it
indirectly and you get your
labs back and you have
high protein or high
lipids, you can wind up
with pseudohyponetremia.
This could also happen
with bladder irrigation.
And in bladder irrigation,
we get an absorption
of large volumes of
osmotically active solutions.
So those are the type
of solutions they
use for bladder
irrigation. It results in
dilution, again, as we
talked about before.
And we can visualize
this here on this slide.
So, like I said,
pseudohypanotremia, the plasma
proteins or lipids occupy
an unexpectedly high volume.
So, the decreased
plasma water is over
diluted while preparing
the sodium, and the
sodium can be falsely
reported as low.
So, we don't actually have
a low sodium here, but our
lab might tell us that when
we get the results. So,
something to be aware of
in our diagnostic pathway.
Now we're going to
move on to hyponatremia
with low osmolality. And this
is going to be our
true hyponatremia,
hypotonic hyponatremia,
it would be called.
And this would be
defined as a plasma
osmolality of less
than 280 milliosmoles.
And there's a lot
of different causes
of hyponatremia,
hypotonic hyponatremia,
that fall under this umbrella.
So we need to look a
little bit further.
First thing we would
do, if we see a patient
has low plasma osmolality
and hyponatremia,
we'd want to look at
the urine osmolality
like we spoke about before. So
that'd be the next
step in our pathway.
If the urine osmolality
is low, less than 100,
the only cause that you
really need to be worrying
about is something called
primary polydipsia.
And primary polydipsia,
as the name I'd
imply, is when you're
drinking too much water.
So the person is
consuming lots and lots
of water, overwhelming
the body's corrective
mechanisms of
normalizing the sodium.
So that's why the urine
osmolality is so low, because
the kidneys are acting
appropriately in diluting
the urine to excrete as
much water as possible. So
everything's working properly,
but you're overwhelming
your body's systems by
consuming too much water.
The remainder of the
causes are going to
have a urine osmolality
above 100 because
something is not
working properly there.
So moving on from here,
now we know that we have
a patient with hyponatremia.
We looked at the plasma
osmolality, it's low,
and the urine osmolality
is low as well. So we're
going to look further.
So these causes here, once
we've ruled out primary
polydipsia by making sure
the urine osmolality is
above 100, here's the
next step in our pathway.
Next step is we're going to be
looking at the volume status.
So remember, increased
volume status, we'd
see peripheral edema,
cites, and the like.
And this happens because
fluids are going to
the extracellular spaces,
their third spacing.
So hypervolemic
patients with a urine
sodium of less than
20, these patients are
typically suffering
from edemptive states.
So some of these states are a
result of congestive
heart failure,
cirrhosis, and
nephrotic syndrome.
In these patients,
they have an effective
arterial blood volume
depletion. And that's due to
decreased perfusion from
low cardiac output in
something like CHF, or
arterial vasodilation.
In cirrhosis or nephrotic
syndrome, the fluid is
leaving the intravascular
space and going into the
extravascular space because
albumin levels are dropping.
So there's insufficient
oncotic pressure
to hold the fluids
within the intravascular
space, and therefore
it goes into the
interstitium, causing
generalized adenia.
Hypervolemic patients
with urine sodium levels
exceeding 20 typically
have advanced renal
disease, and the kidney
is inappropriately
excreting sodium, and
there's an impairment
in free water excretion.
So in severe renal
insufficiency, that can happen.
As you expect, if
urine sodium level is
high, the kidney's not
functioning properly
because we have a patient
with hyponatremia.
Now, what if our
patient had a normal
accelerator fluid
volume status?
This is where we have
an increase in total
body water and sodium
is remaining the same.
And the urine sodium
excretion is greater than
20 milliequivalent,
so concentrated urine.
Most common cause of
this is going to be SIDH,
which we'll talk about
in a little bit later.
We get decreased
water excretion
and increased total body water.
Hypothyroidism and secondary
adrenal insufficiency
both can have a
normal volume status
with hyponatremia,
and both of them are a
result of increased ADH,
so the same mechanism.
Hypothyroidism, it's not
completely understood
why, but there is a result
in increase in ADH, and
therefore a decreased
ability to excrete free
water, so you fail to
maximally dilute the urine.
In secondary adrenal
insufficiency,
we get decreased ACTH
from the hypothalamus
and the hypersecretion of ADH.
The hypersecretion of ADH,
seen with cortisol deficiency,
can also be in part due
to reduction in systemic
blood volume and cardiac
output via an unknown
mechanism, an interruption
of the negative feedback loop
in which cortisol suppresses
ADH, and the ECF volume
is maintained exclusively
because of aldosterone.
So what's the common
theme here with SIDH,
hypothyroidism, and secondary
adrenal insufficiency?
It's for one reason or another
there is increased ADH.
So in a patient who has
normal excellular volume
status with a low plasma
osmolality, a urine
osmolality greater than
100, we should be thinking
of a cause that increases
antidiuretic hormone.
Let's talk about
adrenal insufficiency a
little bit more because
it can be confusing.
So unlike in primary
adrenal insufficiency, the
adrenal gland is not
destroyed in secondary adrenal
insufficiency, which we were
talking about for uvolemic
patients with hypotonic
hypontremia. So since
aldosterone secretion is
primarily under control of
the renin-angiotensin system,
it remains unaffected.
So these patients
with secondary adrenal
insufficiency are uvolemic
and do not have hyperkalemia.
Primary adrenal insufficiency,
on the other hand,
occurs when there's damage
to the adrenal gland
and results in inadequate
cortisol production.
ACTH is going to
increase because the
hypothalamic pituitary
axis attempts
to compensate for
the hypocortisolism.
And hyperpigmentation can
happen, and this can only
happen in primary adrenal
insufficiency. The
reason being is the
underproduction of adrenal cortisol
causes a compensatory
increase in the release
of propiomelanocortin,
POMC, the precursor hormone
that contains both ACTH
and melanocyte-stimulating
hormone. Okay, so in primary,
we'd see hyperkalemia,
skin pigmentation, and
normal to low blood
pressure, whereas in secondary
adrenal insufficiency,
we'd be uvolemic, we
would not have skin
hyperpigmentation, and we
would not have hyperkalemia.
I bring this up, as you'll
see, we're going to talk
about decreased ECF volume
status. So this last
category would be patients
who would have poor skin ****
or something along those
lines. And the reason we'd
see decreased ECF is we
have decreased total body
water, but more of a decrease
in total body sodium.
And we can break this
down with the urine
sodium that's low or
urine sodium that's hot.
With the urine sodium
that's low, so urine sodium
of less than 20, this is
suggesting active renal sodium
retention to compensate
for extra renal losses.
So to say that differently, the
kidneys are working
properly here.
Non-renal causes of
hypovolemic hypometremia
are usually due to
GI loss, so diarrhea,
insensible loss, sweating,
burns of sodium chloride
and water in the absence of
adequate oral replacement.
When the urine sodium
is greater than 20,
that would suggest renal
sodium loss. So we have a
patient with low sodium and
we're getting urine sodium
that's high. So something's
not working within the
kidneys. We could have
something called a salt
wasting nephropathy, and
that's a defect of the kidney,
a reabsorbed sodium and
water then follows it out.
Diuretics, so the most
common cause of diuretic
-induced primary naturesis
is caused by thiazide
diuretics rather than
loop diuretics, actually.
The reason being is that
thiazide diuretics can
cause excessive renal sodium
loss and volume depletion,
and that results in
development of severe
hyponatremia soon after
initiation of therapy. And
finally, hypoaldosterism. So
that's something we talked
about before with primary
adrenal insufficiency.
So if we don't have aldosterone,
we're losing sodium,
and we will see hypovolemia,
increased sodium in the
urine, and hyperkalemia, as
well as hyperpigmentation.
So putting it all together,
just an explanatory
chart, bringing together
everything we said.
first we start with
hyponatremia, then we look at
the osmolality, right?
So we can have normal,
high, or low. And if we
have low osmolality, so less
than 280, and now we have
a urine sodium of greater
than 100, we will look at
the volume status of the
patient, right? This is
bringing us this chart you're
seeing here. So we can have
a patient with hypervolemia,
so total body water higher
than total body sodium,
uvolemia, so no edema or
anything like that, total body
water high and total body
sodium staying the same.
Or we can have a hypovolemic
patient with total body
water decreases, but total
body sodium decreases less.
And in some cases, we
broke this down by the
urine sodium excretion,
the fractional
sodium excretion. In some
cases, we didn't, but
it's just another way
to summarize everything
we're going up that
we discussed above.
Let's go to a question.
So we have a 49-year-old
female presenting to the
ED with complaints of
fatigue, headache, and nausea.
Lab studies show sodium
is 129, so below normal.
Serum osmolality is 250
milliosmoles per kg. So normal
is 275, 290, so low again.
What tests should be
next in our workup to
differentiate the
cause of hyponatremia?
The correct answer here
is urine osmolality.
As we talked about before
in our pathway earlier, we
first want to get a serum
osmolality, which in this
case is low, and next we
want to get urine osmolality.
So, same case, same
patient, fatigue,
headache, nausea, and
now our urine osmolality
comes back and it's
50 osmol per kg.
Normal is 500 to 800.
So, what's the likely cause of
this patient's hyponatremia?
the correct answer
here is primary
polydipsia which I'll
explain why in a second
now which of the following
is the most likely
pathophysiology behind this
patient's hyponatremia the
correct answer here is b so
as we mentioned in primary
polydipsia it's the result
of consuming more water
than the body's regulatory
mechanisms can handle.
So the serum osmolality,
as well as the
urine osmolality,
will be decreased.
And remember, in our
chart that we looked at
before, this is really the
only cause where we had a
low serum osmolality and
a low urine osmolality.
So the bottom line is your
kidneys are functioning
well. It's trying to
get rid of all the
water that you're
consuming for overwhelming
our systems with
too much fluid.
And you should also
go through the other
choices, try to understand
in your mind as you're
studying why these
choices are incorrect and
in which situations
they would be correct.
earlier I mentioned
hyponatremia can result in
cerebral edema which is
a medical emergency and
I want to explain why
so in the normal state
your extracellular fluid
has an osmotic equilibrium
equilibrium with the
intracellular fluid
so there's no net fluid
shift within the brain
So, when a patient has acute
hyponatremia, what's
going to happen here?
Well, the extracellular
fluid is now
hypotonic compared to
the intracellular fluid.
So water is going to be drawn
in as a result of osmosis.
So if water is drawn into
your neurons from the
extracellular fluid, you're
going to get swelling of
the brain, and that's going
to cause cerebral edema.
And you get this
via herniation,
and it can result in death.
What also can happen is
that we get adaptation.
And if we have prolonged
hyponatremia, so not
acute like on that previous
slide, the brain is
going to equalize, and the
brain cells are going to
pump out osmoles into
the extracellular fluid.
First, these osmols are
potassium sodium-based salts,
then the brain is going
to make organic osmols.
And what we're going
to have happen is we're
going to create a new
osmotic equilibrium within
the brain. And this is
going to happen over time.
Obviously, as long as the
patient is still alive and
well, and this is a case
of chronic hyponatremia.
Now, why is this
important to realize?
Well, if we're giving a patient
aggressive correction
of their sodium,
then what we're going to be
doing is the extracellular
fluid is going to wind up
being more concentrated
than the intracellular
fluid because the body has
already come to a new equilibrium
prior to the aggressive
therapy, right? So this
patient has chronic
hyponatremia and we're giving
aggressive sodium correction.
But because the brain
has created these osmols,
so we were initially
hypotonic extracellularly, but
now there's no net flow.
And when we overly correct
with the aggressive therapy
with hypertonic saline,
now we're going to draw
water out of the brain
cells, and this can result
in osmotic demyelination.
Osmotic demyelination
classically affects the
pons, and usually it
happens at least 24 hours
or more after we
aggressively overcorrect.
Patients will have diplopia,
loss of consciousness
and really severe outcomes,
including death can occur.
So key things to be
aware of here is there's
emergencies that can
happen from acute
hyponatremia and
separately from correcting,
overly correcting
chronic hyponatremia once
those brain is formed
a new equilibrium.
So let's look at some
treatment of hyponatremia.
For hypertonic and
isotonic hyponatremia, we
really want to focus on
the underlying cause.
So lipids, excess glucose
within the body. When we
look at true hyponatremia,
hypotonic hyponatremia, we
want to treat the underlying
cause as well, but we
also need to look at the
severity of the hyponatremia.
So how do we determine
the severity?
Well, a few ways.
So we talked about
the duration of
hyponatremia and why
this is important.
So, as if it's chronic,
the brain has already
formed a new equilibrium
by creating its own osmols.
So, we will look whether
it's acute, so the first
day, or chronic, which
is more than 48 hours.
We're going to look at the
severity of the
patient's symptoms.
Mild to moderate symptoms
consist of some headache,
nausea, fatigue, fairly
non-specific, where severe
symptoms, we can see respiratory
rest, coma, seizures,
really troublesome
things in your patient.
And finally, the degree
of hyponatremia. Is
it mild? Is it moderate?
Or is it severe?
Severe meaning it's less than
120 milliequivalents per liter.
The degree is really
important as well.
In treating, we need to talk
about the setting
of the patient,
right?
is the patient appropriate
to be treated inpatient,
or is the patient
appropriate to be treated
outpatient? So inpatient,
this patient needs to
go to emergency department
and be hospitalized.
Outpatient treatment is
appropriate for patients
with high hyponatremia
that's mild, asymptomatic,
moderate hyponatremia,
whereas patients
with severe hyponatremia
and symptomatic, moderate
hyponatremia should be
sent to the hospital.
Different fluids and
medications may be appropriate
depending on the cause. So
in patients where there's
a hormone deficiency or
potassium is playing a
role, we can use the
appropriate medications here.
Again, when a fluid restrict
these patients, we can
give either normal saline
or d5w but again it depends
on the severity and the
cause and not too important
to know the different
types of fluids just be
aware there's multiple
treatments including multiple
types of fluid and medications
we can provide for an
asymptomatic patient with
mild hyponatremia we're
really just using some
isotonic saline or normal
saline at a rate of 0.5 to
1 milliequivalent per liter
per hour. Key thing here,
you don't really have to
know the rate, which we
talked about before, is
raising the sodium 4 to 6
milliequivalents per liter in
a 24-hour period and do
not correct greater than
10 milliequivalents per
liter in any 24-hour period.
So this is the reverse
of what we're talking
about in hyperentremia,
right? So we don't want
to overcorrect too
quickly. We do want to be
more aggressive in patients
with severe symptoms
that have acute
symptomatic hyponatremia.
So the goal of therapy,
again, is to increase sodium
by four to six
milliequivalents per liter, not
exceeding 10. So that
doesn't change. However, the
rate at which we're doing
this quicker because you
want to correct it at a
rapid pace so that you don't
have those severe
consequences of hyponatremia.
So correcting the
sodium is important, but
it's the least important
thing here. The most
important thing is
really based on outcome.
The most important thing
is that our patient
survives and the patient
survives without any
severe consequences. So
that's really what we're
focusing on. It's not just
correcting the sodium.
It's making sure we're
correcting an appropriate
pace and making sure
we're preventing other
complications let's
look at a question here
an 88 year old male
presents the emergency
department with a
complaint of bilateral
lower extremity edema
he has a long-standing
history of cirrhosis
and hyponatremia
the resident notices
sodium level is 119
milliequivalents per
liter and administers
copious hypertonic
saline. Two days later,
the patient is comatose
and eventually dies.
On autopsy, which of
the following brain
structures is most
likely to be affected?
The correct answer here
is A, the PONS. The reason
being, this is a
classic case of osmotic
demyelination syndrome. So
like we talked about, this
occurs with overly rapid
correction of severe
hyponatremia. And by definition,
this is severe because
the serum sodium concentration
is less than 120.
It's been present for more
than two or three days,
right? So this would be
categorized as chronic.
And in chronic, the
brain has already adapted
to make sure there's
equilibrium. So when
we're over aggressive in
correcting the sodium,
osmotic demyelination
can happen, and
this classically
affects the pons.
Let's talk about another case.
We have a 78-year-old
male who's admitted with
hyponatremia and
pneumonia to the hospital.
The patient's plasma
sodium concentration is
129 to start, and then
after three days, it
decreases even further
despite fluid restriction.
A chest CT is done, and
it shows an infrahilar
mass and a post
-obstructive pneumonia.
on past medical history
the patient was an active
smoker and he was treated
for laryngeal carcinoma
15 years earlier with
radiation therapy he
also has a history of renal
cell carcinoma peripheral
vascular disease and
hypothyroidism on the
review of systems the
patient denies any headache
nausea or vomiting just
has some chronic hip pain
that's managed with
acetaminophen and codeine.
Otherwise, the patient
is taking a couple
of medications,
including selostazole,
amoxicillin clavironic acid,
digoxin, diltiazin,
and thyroxine.
He was unipulimic
on exam with no
lymphadenopathy and a
normal chest examination.
Looking at the lab
studies, we can see that a
sodium is low at 125
milliequivalents per liter.
The patient's plasma
osmolality is also low,
and the patient's urine
osmolality is increased.
Taking all that
in, what should be
our working diagnosis
in this patient?
This would be
SIEDH, syndrome of
inappropriate
antidiuretic hormone.
And what's happening
in SIADH is we get
impaired water excretion
and the inability
to suppress ADH, as
the name implies.
So as we talked about,
ADH causes the urine to
be concentrated and
increases total body water.
So if we're inappropriately
doing that, we're
going to see low plasma
sodium urine concentration.
In terms of symptoms,
what do we see?
As we mentioned, symptoms
of hyponatremia are
fairly nonspecific, so
some fatigue, headache,
malaise, as it
worsens, you can get
confusion, altered
mental states,
some GI symptoms, nausea,
vomiting, abdominal pain.
The patient will
be hyponatremic and
have a hypoosmolar
plasma osmolality.
And again, this is
happening because the
patients can have
diarrhea. They're holding
on to all their water,
so it's going to make
sodium decrease in
terms of concentration.
There's a few reasons why
this can happen commonly.
One common reason is
small cell tumors of
the lung, which we can
see the histopathology
on the right in this
picture. Drugs such
as carbamazepine,
cyclophosphamide, SSRIs,
so estetalopram,
Prozac, loxtine, many
other medications as well
can cause it. Surgery can
cause it a lot of times.
Idiopathic is an
unknown cause for many
cases. There's also
hereditary cause of SIDH.
The mainstay of
treatment is fluid
restricting these
patients, so reducing it to
about 800 to one liter
of fluid per day.
This is one of the rare
times where you have combined
salt tablets and loop
diuretics, so loop diuretics
being furosemide with the
salt tablets. We can give
vasopressin receptor antagonists,
and again, like we spoke
about, we do not want to
correct by more than 10
milliequivalents per liter in
the first 24 hours refocusing
key points in the management
of our patient with
hyponatremia first and foremost
we want to know the cause
how do we do this we
go through our history
then our physical exam
and then our lab studies
and diagnostic imaging
then we need to
figure out how to
treat the patient how
fast do we treat and
what to be a monitor.
We also need to assess follow
-up when we should, when
should we expect improvement?
How quickly should we
expect the sodium to improve?
When do we need to re
-evaluate this patient?
And think about different
complications that can happen
from the patient's treatment.
Let's go to another question.
A 55-year-old female presents
the emergency department
with complaints of fatigue
headache and nausea
physical exam reveals no
edema and good skin turgum
lab studies show sodium
is low and serum and urine
osmolality are normal what
is the correct diagnosis
the correct diagnosis
here is hyperlipidemia as
we talked about in our
breakdown of cause of
hyponatremia this is your
pseudo hyponatremia so
lipids are occupying
the space we measure
indirectly. So there
actually isn't hyponatremia
going on. The patient is
hyperlipidemia instead.
And the way that we can
tell this is because
the patient's serum
osmolality is normal, right?
So all our true cases
of hyponatremia,
we have low serum
urine osmolality.
Finally, in summary, we
should be able to distinguish
the clinical features
and complications of
hyponatremia. We should
be able to illustrate the
pathophysiology of
hyponatremia, judge the causes
of hyponatremia, explain
how we treat hyponatremia,
and lastly, you should
be able to explain the
syndrome of inappropriate
antidiuretic hormone.
Below are some core references.
And finally, feel
free to provide
feedback via the link below.
Thank you.